Guide to the Max Lerner Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1927, 1932-1969; Series II
  - Books
    - America as a Civilization
      - America as Civilization - Brandeis University
        - Course syllabus, 1949-1954 (Box 69, Folder 1792 - 1794)
        - Course notes, 1954 fall (Box 69, Folder 1795)
        - Course notes, 1955-1956 (Box 70, Folder 1796 - 1797)
        - Reading lists, 1957-1960 (Box 70, Folder 1798 - 1799)
        - Course syllabus (Box 70, Folder 1800 - 1802)
        - Reading notes (Box 70, Folder 1803 - 1804)
      - Draft, 1957 (Box 71, Folder 1805 - 1807)
      - Drafts, chapters II-IX, 1957 (Box 72, Folder 1808 - 1815)
      - Drafts, chapters IX-XII, 1957 (Box 73, Folder 1816 - 1817)
      - Proofs, 1957 (Box 73, Folder 1818 - 1822)
      - Proofs, 1957 (Box 74, Folder 1823 - 1828)
      - Reviews, 1957 (Box 74, Folder 1829 - 1834)
      - Reviews, 1957 (Box 75, Folder 1835 - 1837)
      - Press clippings, 1957 (Box 75, Folder 1838 - 1842)
    - Unfinished Country
      - Notes, 1959 (Box 75, Folder 1843 - 1852)
      - Notes, 1959 (Box 76, Folder 1853 - 1858)
      - Drafts, forward and part I, 1959 (Box 76, Folder 1859 - 1867)
      - Drafts, parts I-II, 1959 (Box 77, Folder 1868 - 1880)
      - Drafts, parts II-III, 1959 (Box 78, Folder 1881 - 1896)
      - Drafts, parts III-IV, 1959 (Box 79, Folder 1897 - 1910)
      - Drafts, part V, 1959 (Box 80, Folder 1911 - 1924)
      - Press clippings, 1959 (Box 81, Folder 1925 - 1928)
    - Indian Journal - Foreward mss., unpublished, 1960 (Box 81, Folder 1929)
    - Triumph of Laissez-Faire - mss., 1963 (Box 81, Folder 1930 - 1933)
    - Life and Thought of Thomas Jefferson - introduction mss., 1968 (Box 81, Folder 1934 - 1937)
    - De Tocqueville in America
      - Mss., 1960 (Box 82, Folder 1938 - 1945)
      - Proof, 1960 (Box 83, Folder 1946)
    - Collected Works of J.S. Mill - notes, 1961 (Box 84, Folder 1947 - 1948)
    - Introduction to Unfinished Society by Herbert von Borch, 1962
      - Mss., 1962 (Box 84, Folder 1949 - 1950)
      - Proof, 1962 (Box 84, Folder 1951 - 1953)
    - Age of Overkill
      - Notes, 1962 (Box 84, Folder 1954 - 1958)
      - Notes, 1962 (Box 85, Folder 1959 - 1972)
      - Notes, 1962 (Box 86, Folder 1973 - 1979)
      - Notes, T. V. series, 1962 (Box 86, Folder 1980 - 1986)
      - Notes, T. V. series, 1962 (Box 87, Folder 1987 - 2001)
      - Commentary, chapter II, 1962 (Box 87, Folder 2002)
      - Commentary, chapters II, IV-VI, 1962 (Box 88, Folder 2003 - 2009)
      - Age of Overkill - Brandeis University, course notes, 1962 (Box 88, Folder 2010)
      - Mss. chapters I-VI, 1962 (Box 88, Folder 2011 - 2018)
      - Final mss. chapters I-VI, 1962 (Box 89, Folder 2019 - 2025)
      - Proof, 1961 (Box 89, Folder 2025)
    - Supreme Court - unpublished mss., Undated (Box 90, Folder 2026)
    - Freud and Marx - unpublished mss., Undated (Box 90, Folder 2027 - 2028)
    - Bibliographies, Undated (Box 90, Folder 2028a)
- Photographs, Press Clippings, and Memorabilia, 1955-1969; Series III
  PHOTOGRAPHS, PRESS CLIPPINGS, AND MEMORABILIA is divided into three sections: photographs, press clippings, and memorabilia. Within these sections, however, the items are filed in no particular order. The only exception is the last box containing tape recordings of some of Lerner's radio and television broadcasts which are filed chronologically; a list of these tapes is appended to this register.
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 91, Folder 2029 - 2036)
  - Press clippings (Box 92, Folder 2037 - 2048)
  - Press clippings (Box 93, Folder 2049 - 2062)
  - Memorabilia (Box 94, Folder 2063 - 2071)
  - Memorabilia (Box 95, Folder 2072 - 2081)
  - Memorabilia (Box 96, Folder 2082 - 2090)
  - Articles about Lerner (Box 96, Folder 2091)
  - Articles about Lerner (Box 97, Folder 2092)
  - Memoranda from P.M. (Box 97, Folder 2093 - 2096)
  - Memorandum of conversation with Robert S. McNamara, 1966 (Box 97, Folder 2097)
  - References for columns (Box 97, Folder 2098 - 2099)
  - Royalty statements (Box 97, Folder 2100 - 2102)
  - Brandeis University Yearbooks
    - 1953 (Box 97, Folder 2103)
    - 1957 (Box 98, Folder 2104)
  - M. A. thesis - Washington University, 1923 (Box 98, Folder 2105)
  - Alumni citation - Washington University, 1959 (Box 98, Folder 2106)
  - Tapes, nos. 1-49
    Separated Materials
    Tapes transferred to Historical Sound Recordings, SML
    - Moscow Report series
      - Tape 1 - (1), 1958 April 30
      - Tape 2 - (2), 1957 November 23
      - Tape 3 - (3), 1958 June 5
      - Tape 4 - (4), Undated
    - World Politics series
      - Tape 5 - (1), 1960 January 4
      - Tapes 6-9 - (2-5), 1960 January 8
      - Tapes 10-11 - (61-62), 1960 November 8
      - Tapes 12-13 - (71-72), 1960 November 14
      - Tapes 14-19 - (81-86), 1960 November 21
      - Tapes 20-25 - (91-96), 1960 November 28
      - Tapes 26-29 - (101-104), 1960 December 5
    - Age of Overkill series
      - Tapes 30-31, Undated
      - Tape 32 - A Woman's World, 1962 March 22
      - Tape 33 - Reader's Digest interview: "The Vanishing American Father", 1965 January
      - Tape 34 - American Forces Network, Berlin, 1966
      - Tape 35 - University of Bridgeport Address, 1966
      - Tape 36 - United States Department of Agriculture Address, 1967 May 11
      - Tape 37 - Chicago Council on Foreign Relations Address, 1967 September 28
      - Tape 38 - Providence College Forum, 1967 December 5
      - Tape 39 - "Far Out America: Is There a Revolution in Values?", 1968 March 21
      - Tapes 40-41 - Center for Liberal Studies, American University, 1968 March 26
      - Tapes 42-43 - "Our People," and Tanglewood Symposium on Music Education, Undated
      - Tapes 44-49 - unmarked tapes: no title (1-6), Undated
- Books in the Max Lerner Papers, Series IV
  - Books authored or edited by Max Lerner
    - Actions and Passions: Notes on the Multiple Revolution of Our Time. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1949 (Box 100)
    - America as Civilization: Life and Thought in the United States Today. London: Jonathan Cape [Foreign editions in Arabic (3 vols.); French (1 vol.); German (1 vol.); Portuguese (3 of 4 vols.); Spanish (2 vols.)], 1958
    - Democracy in America. Alexis de Tocqueville, edited by J. P. Mayer and Max Lerner. New York: Harper and Row [2 copies], 1966 (Box 100)
    - Education and a Radical Humanism: Notes toward a Theory of the Educational Crisis. Columbus, Ohio: Ohio State University Press, 1962
    - Education and the Disadvantaged American. The Educational Policies Commission. Washington, D. C.: National Education Association of the United States [Lerner was a member of the Commission], 1962 (Box 100)
    - Essential Works of John Stuart Mill. Edited and with an introduction by Max Lerner. New York: Bantam Books, 1961 and Bantam Matrix. [5 copies], 1965 (Box 100)
    - Ideas are Weapons: The History and Uses of Ideas. New York: Viking Press, 1939 (Box 101)
    - Ideas for the Ice Age. New York: Viking Press, 1941 (Box 101)
    - International Organization after the War: Roads to World Security. Analysis by Max Lerner and Edna Lerner. Washington, D.C.: National Association of the Secondary-School Principals and National Council for the Social Studies [pamphlet in the Problems in American Life series, unit no. 15], 1943 (Box 101)
    - It Is Later Than You Think: The Need for a Militant Democracy. London: W. & R. Chambers [foreign edition in Spanish], 1939 (Box 101)
    - The Mind and Faith of Justice Holmes: His Speeches, Essays, Letters and Judicial Opinions. Selected and edited with introduction and commentary by Max Lerner. Boston: Little, Brown and Co., 1945 (Box 101)
    - The Portable Veblen. Edited, with an introduction by Max Lerner. New York: Viking Press, 1958 (Box 101)
    - Public Journal: Marginal Notes on Wartime America. New York: Viking Press, 1945 (Box 101)
    - Third Battle for France. New York: Union for Democratic Action Educational Fund, Inc. [pamphlet], 1945 (Box 101)
    - The Unfinished Country: A Book of American Symbols. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1959 (Box 101)
  - Articles and chapters by Max Lerner
    - "America and the New World" and "Review of 'Abraham Lincoln, the War Years'." In First Person Singular. Sharon Brown. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co., xii. [The articles mentioned are not included in this volume.], 1941 (Box 101)
    - "American Leadership in a Harsh Age." In The Annals of The American Academy of Political and Social Science, Vol. 216. Editor Thorsten Sellin. 117-124., 1941 July (Box 101)
    - "Big Technology and Neutral Technicians." In Perspectives USA, No. 14. 116-129. [1 copy each in French, Italian, and German], 1956 January (Box 101)
    - "Charles Beard's Political Theory." In Charles A. Beard, An Appraisal. Edited by Howard K. Beale. [Lexington, Kentucky?]: University of Kentucky Press, 25-45., 1954 (Box 101)
    - "Charlie." In Hello, Hollywood!: A Book about the Movies and the People Who Make Them. Allen Rivkin and Laura Kerr. New York: Doubleday & Co., 279-280., 1962 (Box 101)
    - Commentary on "The Target." In Radio in Wartime. Sherman H. Dryer. New York: Greenberg, 128-134., 1942 (Box 101)
    - "The Competition of Ideas." In Freedom of the Press Today: A Clinical Examination by 28 Specialists. Assembled with an introduction by Harold L. Ickes. New York: The Vanguard Press, 181-186. [Article has been removed from this copy of the book.], 1941 (Box 101)
    - "Crime as Social Disorder." In Organized Crime in America. Gus Tyler. Ann Arbor, Michigan: University of Michigan Press, 79-86., 1962 (Box 101)
    - "The Crisis State." In Leviathan in Crisis. Compiled and edited by Waldo R. Browne. New York: The Viking Press, 275-281., 1946 (Box 101)
    - "Decline of the Small Town." In Current Thinking and Writing. Edited by Joseph M. Bachelor, Ralph L. Henry, and Rachel Salisbury. New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts, 253-258., 1960 (Box 101)
    - "Democracy and Foreign Policy." In Proceedings of the Seventh Conference of Teachers of International Law and Related Subjects. Washington D. C.: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 84-89., 1941 (Box 102)
    - "Democracy in a Civilization Based on Science." In A Revaluation of Our Civilization. Frederick R. Wulsin, et al. Albany, New York: The Argus Press, 145-168., 1944 (Box 102)
    - "Discovery of the 'Irrational': Personal and Collective." In The Planning of Change: Readings in the Applied Behavioral Sciences. Edited by Warren G. Bennis, Kenneth D. Benne, and Robert Chin. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 116-122. [2 copies], 1961 (Box 102)
    - Discussion of "The First World War and American Democracy," by George E. Mowry. In War as a Social Institution: The Historians Perspective. Edited by Jesse D. Clarkson and Thomas C. Cochran. New York: Columbia University Press, 184-188., 1941 (Box 102)
    - Discussion of "The Interrelation of Cultures." In Social Research: An International Quarterly of Political and Social Science, Vol. 3, no. 4, 334-337. [discussion has been removed from this copy], 1937 September (Box 102)
    - "The Divine Right of Judges," "The Fate of the Supreme Court," "Freedom of the Opinion Industries," and "The 'TVA' for the Opinion Industries." In The People, Politics, and the Politician: Readings in American Government. Edited by A. N. Christensen and E. M. Kirkpatrick. New York: Henry Holt & Co., 577-582. [additional copy of reprint under the title Running the Country: An Anthology of American Politics in Action. New York: Henry Holt & Co.], 1941, 1946 (Box 102)
    - "Education and American Civilization." In The American Secondary School. David B. Austin, et al. New York: College Entrance Examination Board, 66-74., 1959 (Box 102)
    - "The Enigma of FDR." In The Roosevelt Era. Edited by Milton Crane. New York: Boni & Gaer, 605-610., 1947 (Box 102)
    - "The Flowering of Latter-Day Man." In The American Scholar Reader. Edited by Hiram Haydn and Betsy Saunders. New York: Atheneum Publishers, 1960 (Box 102)
    - Forewords, Introductions, and Prefaces (Box 102)
      - Against the Law. Peter Wildblood. New York: Julian Messner, Inc., 1959 (Box 102)
      - The Fifty-Minute Hour: A Collection of True Psychoanalytic Tales. Robert Lindner. New York: Rinehart & Co., 1955 (Box 102)
      - Final Judgment: The Story of Nuremberg. Victor H. Bernstein. New York: Boni & Gaer, ix-xii., 1947 (Box 102)
      - The Iron Heel. Jack London. New York: The MacMillan Co., vii-xiii., 1958 (Box 102)
      - The Myth of the Total State: Europe's Last Bid for World Rule. Guenter Reimann. New York: William Morrow and Co., 9-18., 1941 (Box 102)
      - Pioneer's Progress. Alvin Johnson. Lincoln, Nebraska: University of Nebraska Press, 1960 (Box 102)
      - The Prince and The Discourses. Niccolò Machiavelli. New York: Modern Library, xxv-xlvi., 1950 (Box 102)
      - Randolph Bourne. Louis Filler. Washington, D. C.: American Council on Public Affairs, v-vii., 1943 (Box 103)
      - Sex and the College Girl. Gael Green. New York: The Dial Press, 9-11. [missing], 1964 (Box 103)
      - St. Michael and the Dragon: Memoirs of a Paratrooper. Pierre Leulliette. Translated by John Edmonds. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co., vii-xiii., 1964 (Box 103)
      - The Unfinished Society. Herbert Von Borch. Translated by Mary Ilford. New York: Hawthorn Books, Inc., 5-7., 1962 (Box 103)
      - The Wealth of Nations. Adam Smith. Edited by Edwin Cannan. New York: Random House, v-x., 1937 (Box 103)
    - "Freedom: Image and Reality." In Safeguarding Civil Liberties Today. Carl L. Becker, et al. Ithaca New York: Cornell University Press, 33-57., 1945 (Box 103)
    - "To Halt this Land." In Return to Freedom: The Affairs of Our Time and Their Impact Upon Youth. Edited by Thomas H. Johnson. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 144-152., 1944 (Box 103)
    - "How does this war differ from other American wars?" In America Organizes to Win the War: A Handbook on the American War Effort. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co., [2 copies.] 43-58., 1942 (Box 103)
    - "The Human Voyage." In The Kafka Problem. Edited by Angel Flores. New York: New Directions, 38-46., 1946 (Box 103)
    - "The Idea of American Civilization." In The Character of Americans. Edited by Michael McGiffert. Homewood, Illinois: The Dorsey Press, 10-20., 1968 (Box 103)
    - Important Books of the Last One Hundred Years--Political Science, Economics, and Sociology. In The Practice of Book Selection: Papers Presented Before the Library Institute at the University of Chicago August 1939. Edited by Louis R. Wilson. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 40-60. [Article has been removed from this copy of the book.], 1940 (Box 103)
    - "Lincoln as War Leader." In The Harbrace Omnibus. Edited by Harry B. Reed, et al. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co., 147-152., 1942 (Box 103)
    - "Lincoln as War Leader." In Readings in Exposition. Edited by Harry B. Reed and Julia Norton McCorkle. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co., 147-152., 1942 (Box 103)
    - "The Meaning of Group Experience in the Current Scene." In The Social Welfare Forum, 1955. National Conference of Social Work. New York: Columbia University Press, 85-97. (Box 103)
    - "My Father 'Moved.'" In To Be a Father. Edited by Alvin Schwartz. New York: Crown Publishers, 247-249. [missing], 1967 (Box 103)
    - "The Negro American and His City: Person In Place and Culture." In Daedalus: Journal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences vol. 97, no. 4 [missing], 1968 fall (Box 103)
    - "On the Age of Overkill." In Talks with Social Scientists. Edited by Charles F. Madden. Carbondale, Illinois: Southern Illinois University Press, 143-159., 1968 (Box 103)
    - "On Whose Behalf is the Dream being Dreamt?" In Environment and Change: The Next Fifty Years. Edited by William R. Ewald. Bloomington, Indiana: Indiana University Press, 176-181., 1968 (Box 103)
    - "Our Changing Society." In The Climate of Book Selection: Social Influence on School and Public Libraries. Edited by J. Periam Danton. Berkeley: University of California School of Librarianship, 3-11., 1959 (Box 103)
    - "The Pattern of Dictatorship." In Readings in Social Science Vol. 3. East Lansing, Michigan: Michigan State University Press, 436-443., 1956 (Box 103)
    - "The Pattern of Dictatorship." In Dictatorship in the Modern World. Edited by Guy Stanton Ford. Minneapolis, Minnesota: The University of Minnesota Press, [2 editions]. 1-23., 1935, 1939 (Box 103)
    - "Politics and Total War." In Toward International Organization. Howard Robinson, et al. New York: Harper & Brothers, 69-91., 1942 (Box 103)
    - "Proceedings of the Conference on Blumer's Analysis." In Critiques of Research in the Social Sciences: I. Herbert Blumer. Ann Arbor, Michigan: Edwards Brothers, 101-202. [Text includes transcript of a panel conversation in which Lerner participated.], 1949 (Box 103)
    - "Profiles of the Vanishing Father." In The Challenge to Women. Edited by Seymour M. Farber and Roger H. L. Wilson. New York: Basic Books, 63-72., 1966 (Box 103)
    - The Range of Reason. Jacques Maritain. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, [Lerner is cited on pages 134, 137, 138, and 164.], 1952 (Box 104)
    - "Ride in the Whirlwind." In The Revised College Omnibus. Edited by James Dow McCallum in collaboration with Marston Balch, et al. New York: Harcourt, Brace & Co., 173-176., 1939 (Box 104)
    - "Russia and America: A Critical Partnership." In Treasury for the Free World. Edited by Ben Raeburn with an introduction by Ernest Hemingway. New York: Arco Publishing Co., 1946 (Box 104)
    - "Science and American Power." In Roots of Political Behavior: Introduction to Government and Politics. Compiled by Richard Carlton Snyder and H. Hubert Wilson. New York: American Book Co., 441-446., 1949 (Box 104)
    - "The Shadow of Capitalism." In Our Neurotic Age: A Consultation. Edited by Samuel D. Schmalhausen. New York: Farrar & Rinehart, 350-374., 1932 (Box 104)
    - "Six Revolutions in American Life." In The Revolutionary Theme in Contemporary America. Edited by Thomas R. Ford. Lexington, Kentucky: University of Kentucky Press, 1-20., 1967 (Box 104)
    - "The Slaying of the European Father." In American Thought 1947. New York: The Gresham Press, 425-431. (Box 104)
    - "The Supreme Court and American Capitalism." In Franklin D. Roosevelt and the Supreme Court. Edited by Alfred Haines Cope and Fred Krinsky. Boston: D. C. Heath and Co., 39-59., 1952 (Box 104)
    - "Testimony by Max Lerner before the Television Advisory Panel." In Educational Television: The Next Ten Years. Institute for Communication Research, Stanford University. Stanford, California: Institute for Communication Research, Stanford University, 118-122., 1962 (Box 104)
    - "Toward an American Society." In Proceedings of the National Conference of Social Workers. New York: Columbia University Press, 55-64., 1947 (Box 104)
    - "The Training of a Teacher Elite." In Teacher Education for the Future. American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education Twelfth Yearbook. Chicago: American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 12-27., 1959 (Box 104)
    - "Wasteland." In Patterns for Living. Edited by Oscar James Campbell, Justine Van Gundy, and Caroline Shrodes. New York: The MacMillan Co., 1940 (Box 104)
    - "Wendell L. Wilkie, One World, 1943." In An American Primer 2 vols. Edited by Daniel J. Boorstin. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, II.863-882. [article edited by Lerner][1968 edition is missing], 1966 (Box 104)
    - "What is Usable in Veblen." In The New Republic Anthology 1915-1935. Edited by Groff Conklin. New York: Dodge Publishing Co., 496-504., 1936 (Box 104)
    - "What Kind of American Civilization." In The Social Welfare Forum, 1957. National Conference on Social Welfare. New York: Columbia University Press, 42-50. (Box 105)
    - "What Makes a Social Problem." In Contemporary Social Problems. Edited by Louis Wirth. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 13-21., 1939 (Box 105)
    - "World Image and World Order." In Twice a Year, A Book of Literature, the Arts, and Civil Liberties Vols. 10-11, 29-39., 1943 (Box 105)
    - "You and I and Silence." In The Poets of the Future. Edited by Henry T. Schnittkind. Boston: The Stratford Co. [poem], 1925 (Box 105)
  - Published materials not pertaining to Max Lerner [9 volumes] (Box 105)
- Additional Material, Accession 1982-M-005
  - Correspondence, 1942-1979, undated; Series I
    Correspondence (.75 linear feet) is arranged chronologically; the bulk of it is from 1945 to 1969. It relates to Max Lerner's career in journalism and his writings. There is a large amount of correspondence with various publishers and editors, particularly Walter Minton at G. P. Putnam's Sons. Other letters concern Lerner's travels, speaking engagements, and participation in conferences and various media projects. Lerner also corresponded with many prominent writers, artists, politicians, and journalists on national and world politics and current events.
    There are letters from the 1940s relating to Lerner's work on PM, and to and from his editor, Merle Thompson. In addition, there is correspondence on World War II; the Soviet Union; Edmund Wilson's attack on Stalin in 1946; Trotsky; post-war politics in France; anti-Semitism and Israel; the United Auto Workers; the Douglas nomination to the Supreme Court; the financial woes of Black Mountain College; and national and presidential politics. Items of particular interest include a copy of a 1945 letter from Senator Robert Taft on immigration restrictions and Jewish refugees, and letters from 1945 describing the liberation of a concentration camp in Germany and the writer's meeting with a Russian officer who was a great admirer of Lerner.
    Correspondence from the 1950s documents Lerner's interest in national politics and homosexuality, and his work with several Jewish organizations. Prominent correspondents include Alfred C. Kinsey in 1954, criticizing Lerner's interpretation of his work; Langston Hughes in 1955, writing about his character "Simple;" and Edmund Wilson in 1956, discussing Rosenberg trial.
    There are many letters from the 1960s concerning Lerner's work on television station WGBH's "Age of Overkill" series and his book by the same title. There are letters on the assassination of President John F. Kennedy; the Fanny Hill obscenity trial; Lerner's work on the New York Post; and the war in Vietnam. Lerner's correspondence with Howard Zinn and Horace Bond in 1960, on African-American education in the South, and the Louis Malle in 1970, on a proposed film on utopian societies, is particularly interesting. Some of Lerner's writings are found in the 1960s correspondence, including a 1968 paper delivered at the American Medical Association, "Technology and Creativeness;" a 1969 speech delivered at the Texas Library Association; and a 1970 poem.
    The correspondence also includes several undated notes and letters, chiefly from readers, including one on J. Edgar Hoover's alleged homosexuality.
    - 1942-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 27)
    - 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 28 - 36)
    - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Writings, 1942-circa 1980; Series II